Chapter 76.
The battering ram.
Air quitting for the nons the sperm whale's head, I would have you, as a
sensible physiologist simply, particularly remark its front aspect in
all its compacted collectedness. I would have you investigate it now with the
sole view of forming to yourself some unexaggerated intelligent estimate of
whatever battering ram power may be lodged there. Here is a vital point for
you must either satisfactorily settle this matter with yourself or forever
remain an infidel as to one of the most appalling but not the less true events
perhaps anywhere to be found in all recorded history.
You observe that in the ordinary swimming position of the sperm whale,
the front of his head presents an almost wholly vertical plane to the water. You
observe that the lower part of that front slopes considerably backwards so
as to furnish more of a retreat for the long socket which receives the boomlike
lower jaw. You observe that the mouth is entirely under the head, much in the
same way indeed, as though your own mouth were entirely under your chin.
Moreover, you observe that the whale has no external nose, and that what nose he
has, his spout hole, is on the top of his head. You observe that his eyes and
ears are at the sides of his head, nearly onethird of his entire length from the front.
Wherefore you must now have perceived that the front of the sperm whale's head
is a dead blind wall without a single organ or tender prominence of any sort
whatsoever. Furthermore, you are now to consider that only in the extreme lower
backward sloping part of the front of the head is there the slightest vestage
of bone. And not till you get near 20 ft from the forehead do you come to the
full cranial development.
So that this whole enormous boneless mass is as one wad. Finally though as
will soon be revealed its contents partly comprise the most delicate oil.
Yet you are now to be apprised of the nature of the substance which so
impregnably invests all that apparent effeminisy. In some previous place I
have described to you how the blubber wraps the body of the whale as the rind
wraps an orange. Just so with the head, but with this difference about the head
this envelope, though not so thick, is of a boneless toughness inestimable by
any man who has not handled it. The severest pointed harpoon, the sharpest
lance darted by the strongest human arm, impotently rebounds from it. It is as
though the forehead of the sperm whale were paved with horses hoofs. I do not
think that any sensation lurks in it.
Beth think yourself also of another thing. When two large loaded indiummen
to crowd and crush towards each other in the docks, what do the sailors do? They
do not suspend between them at the point of coming contact any merely hard
substance like iron or wood. No, they hold there a large round wad of toe and
cork enveloped in the thickest and toughest of oxhide that bravely and
uninjured takes the jam which would have snapped all their oak and hand spikes
and iron crowbars. By itself this sufficiently illustrates the obvious
fact I drive at. But supplementary to this, it is hypothetically occurred to
me that as ordinary fish possess what is called a swimming bladder in them,
capable at will of distension or contraction, and as the sperm whale, as
far as I know, has no such provision in him, considering too the otherwise
inexplicable manner in which he now depresses his head alltogether beneath
the surface, and an swims with it high elevated out of the water, considering
the unobstructed elasticity of its envelope, considering the unique interior of his head. It has
hypothetically occurred to me, I say, that those mystical lungselled
honeycombs there may possibly have some hitherto unknown and unsuspected
connection with the outer air, so as to be susceptible to atmospheric distension
and contraction. If this be so, fancy the irresistibleness of that might to
which the most impalpable and destructive of all elements contributes.
Now mark unairringly impelling this dead impregnable uninjurable wall and this
most buoyant thing within there swims behind it all a mass of tremendous life
only to be adequately estimated as piled wood is by the cord and all obedient to
one vition as the smallest insect. So that when I shall hereafter detail to
you all the specialties and concentrations of potency everywhere
lurking in this expansive monster, when I shall show you some of his more
inconsiderable braining feats, I trust you will have renounced all ignorant
incredul and be ready to abide by this, that though the sperm whale stove a
passage through the ismas of Darion, and mixed the Atlantic with the Pacific, you
would not elevate one hair of your eyebrow. For unless you own the whale,
you are but a provincial and sentimentalist in truth. But clear truth
is a thing for salamander giants only to encounter. How small the chances for the
provincials then? What befell the weakling youth lifting the dread goddess's veil at Lis.